<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Java on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>/tags/java/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Java on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 17:12:39 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/java/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>SQL Server 2019 Extensibility Framework &amp; Java - Null Values</title>
      <link>/2018/12/19/sql-server-2019-extensibility-framework--java---null-values/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 17:12:39 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/19/sql-server-2019-extensibility-framework--java---null-values/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is the third post where I look at the Java extension in SQL Server, i.e. the ability to execute Java code from inside SQL Server. The previous two posts are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/2018/12/02/sql-server-2019-extensibility-framework--java---hello-world/&#34;&gt;SQL Server 2019 Extensibility Framework &amp;amp; Java - Hello World&lt;/a&gt;: We looked at installing and enabling the Java extension, as well as some very basic Java code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/2018/12/08/sql-server-2019-extensibility-framework--java---passing-data/&#34;&gt;SQL Server 2019 Extensibility Framework &amp;amp; Java - Passing Data&lt;/a&gt;: In this post we discussed what is required to pass data back and forth between SQL Server and Java.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post we look at something related to the &lt;a href=&#34;/2018/12/08/sql-server-2019-extensibility-framework--java---passing-data/&#34;&gt;data passing post&lt;/a&gt;; how to handle null values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 49</title>
      <link>/2018/12/09/interesting-stuff---week-49/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2018 07:18:55 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/09/interesting-stuff---week-49/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;data science&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;data in general&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;distributed computing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SQL Server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;transactions (both db as well as non db)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and other &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog-post is the &amp;ldquo;roundup&amp;rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SQL Server 2019 Extensibility Framework &amp; Java - Passing Data</title>
      <link>/2018/12/08/sql-server-2019-extensibility-framework--java---passing-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2018 19:52:11 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/08/sql-server-2019-extensibility-framework--java---passing-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is the second post about SQL Server 2019 Extensibility Framework and the Java language extensions. In the first post, &lt;a href=&#34;/2018/12/02/sql-server-2019-extensibility-framework--java---hello-world/&#34;&gt;SQL Server 2019 Extensibility Framework &amp;amp; Java - Hello World&lt;/a&gt;, we looked at how to install and enable the Java language extensions, and we also wrote some pretty basic Java code to ensure it all worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post we look at how we can pass data back and forth between SQL Server and Java.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 48</title>
      <link>/2018/12/02/interesting-stuff---week-48/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2018 14:43:12 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/02/interesting-stuff---week-48/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;data science&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;data in general&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;distributed computing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SQL Server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;transactions (both db as well as non db)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and other &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog-post is the &amp;ldquo;roundup&amp;rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SQL Server 2019 Extensibility Framework &amp; Java - Hello World</title>
      <link>/2018/12/02/sql-server-2019-extensibility-framework--java---hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2018 09:36:34 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/02/sql-server-2019-extensibility-framework--java---hello-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The SQL Server 2016 release introduced the &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server Extensibility Framework&lt;/strong&gt; (EF), which gives us the ability to, from inside SQL Server, execute code in an external language runtime environment. SQL Server 2016 supports R as external runtime, and Microsoft added Python to supported runtimes in the SQL Server 2017 release. The important part about the EF is that the runtime is outside of the core database engine, but we call it from inside SQL Server via the stored procedure &lt;code&gt;sp_execute_external_script&lt;/code&gt;. We can push data from SQL Server queries to the external runtime, and consume data, (resultsets, output parameters) from the external runtime back in SQL Server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&lt;/strong&gt; You can read more about the actual implementation of the external runtimes and &lt;code&gt;sp_execute_external_script&lt;/code&gt; in my &lt;a href=&#34;/sql_server_2k16_r_services/&#34;&gt;SQL Server R Services Series&lt;/a&gt; posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In SQL Server 2019 Microsoft added the ability to execute custom Java code along the same lines we execute R and Python, and this blog post intends to give an introduction of how to install and enable the Java extension, as well as execute some very basic Java code. In future posts, I drill down how to pass data back and forth between SQL Server and Java.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SQL Server 2019 for Linux in Docker on Windows</title>
      <link>/2018/09/29/sql-server-2019-for-linux-in-docker-on-windows/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 12:06:09 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/29/sql-server-2019-for-linux-in-docker-on-windows/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By the time I publish this blog post &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/ignite&#34;&gt;MS Ignite&lt;/a&gt; is over. During Ignite, Microsoft announced quite a few new things, amongst them &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server 2019&lt;/strong&gt; with a whole lot of new features and functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I touched briefly on some of them in my &lt;a href=&#34;/2018/09/24/what-is-new-in-sql-server-2019-public-preview/&#34;&gt;What is New in SQL Server 2019 Public Preview&lt;/a&gt; post. A couple of things that caught my eye were that &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server 2019 for Linux&lt;/strong&gt; now supports In-Database analytics, what we know as &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server Machine Learning Services&lt;/strong&gt; (R and Python), as well as the Java language extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&lt;/strong&gt; You may ask yourself what the Java language extension is; well, that is the ability to access Java code from T-SQL. It is a little bit like SQLCLR, but it executes outside of the SQL Server memory and process space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing that I never really have played around with &lt;em&gt;SQL Server for Linux&lt;/em&gt;, mostly due to that in previous versions (2017) it did not have support for In-Database analytics, I thought that now would be a good time to have a look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is New in SQL Server 2019 Public Preview</title>
      <link>/2018/09/24/what-is-new-in-sql-server-2019-public-preview/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 19:17:06 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/24/what-is-new-in-sql-server-2019-public-preview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you read my roundup for &lt;a href=&#34;/2018/09/23/interesting-stuff---week-38/&#34;&gt;week 38&lt;/a&gt;, which I published yesterday, you probably noticed that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/ignite&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MS Ignite&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; started today. I mentioned in the post that I was particularly interested in some of the &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server&lt;/strong&gt; sessions, as they looked very interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, even before the sessions started, Microsoft released SQL Server 2019 CTP 2.0 for public preview and, naturally, I jumped on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/evalcenter/evaluate-sql-server-2019-ctp&#34;&gt;download link&lt;/a&gt; and started downloading. I managed to get to the link in time before the rest of the world started the download, so I managed to get it down and then did an install.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of this post is about my initial findings mostly in the SQL Server Machine Learning Services space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&lt;/strong&gt; I have looked at SQL Server 2019 the grand total of an hour, so this is a short post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>